Guide to the Juanita Morris Kreps Papers, 1921-2001 and undated RL.00789
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Juanita Morris Kreps papers
1921-2001 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Kreps, Juanita Morris
RL.00789
41.1 Linear Feet
Juanita Morris Kreps was born January 11, 1921, in Lynch (Harlan Co.), Kentucky. She was Professor of Economics at Duke University (1958-1977), where she held the James B. Duke professorship (1972-1977), also serving as Dean of the Woman's College (1969-1972) and University Vice President (1973-1977). She then was appointed U.S. Secretary of Commerce in 1977 for the Carter Administration and served for two years. Kreps's papers span the years 1921-2001, and contain incoming and outgoing correspondence (1968-1979), many speech drafts (1967-1997), twenty photograph albums, fifteen scrapbooks, 692 color and 595 black-and-white loose photographs, and over 100 negatives. There are also briefing books, reports, notes, minutes, appointee recommendations, speech drafts, and other documents relating to Kreps's cabinet-level work. The audience for her speeches included university students as well as alumni and women's organizations; speech topics focus on education for women, the value of women's work, age and gender in economics and economic markets, and leisure and economic growth. Other correspondence documents Kreps's career positions, some more fully than others, including Secretary of Commerce; Duke University Dean of the Woman's College, especially relating to the merger of the Woman's College and Trinity College; Public Director of the New York Stock Exchange Board; and Women's Research and Education Institute Board of Directors. Photograph albums and scrapbooks detail visits to the USSR, China, and Japan and contain clippings regarding her cabinet position.
Approximately 19,925 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Juanita Morris Kreps Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2001.
Biographical Note
Chronology List
1921, January 11 Born in Lynch (Harlan Co.), Kentucky
1942 B.A., Berea College
1944 M.A., Duke University
1944 Married Clifton H. Kreps, Jr.
1945-1946 Instructor, Denison University, Ohio
1947-1950 Assistant Professor of Economics, Denison University
1948 Ph.D, Duke University
1952-1954 Lecturer in Economics, Hofstra University, NY
1954-1955 Lecturer in Economics, Queens College (now City University of New York), NY
1958-1961 Visiting Instructor and Assistant Professor, Duke University
1963-1968 Associate Professor, Duke University
1964 Member of board of directors of National Council on the Aging
1968-1972 Professor of Economics, Duke University
1969-1972 Served as Dean of Duke Woman's College and Assistant Provost
1971-1977 Member of Board of Directors, Educational Testing Service
1972-1977 Named James B. Duke Professor of Economics
1972-1974 Vice-chair of board of directors of North Carolina Manpower Commission
1972-1977 Member of Board of Directors of New York Stock Exchange
1973-1977 Served as Vice-President of Duke University
1976 North Carolina Public Service Award
1977-1979 Served as U.S. Secretary of Commerce for the Carter presidency
1978 Received Stephen Wise Award from American Jewish Congress
1979 Appointed Trustee of Duke Endowment
1982 Received Distinguished Public Service Award from North Carolina Citizens Association
2010, July 5 Died in Durham, North Carolina
Collection Overview
The Juanita Kreps Papers span the years 1921-2001, mainly documenting Kreps's career as an economist, academic administrator, and U.S. Secretary of Commerce for the Carter administration. The two series holding the majority of the materials, the Secretary of Commerce and Speeches Series, concern her service in the political and public spheres respectively. The Secretary of Commerce Series is arranged in the following seven subseries: Appointment Books and Calendars, Appointment and Confirmation Process, Correspondence, Notes, Subject Files, Scrapbooks, and Photographs. Photograph albums and scrapbooks detail visits to the USSR, China, and Japan and contain clippings regarding her cabinet position. There are also separate series for correspondence and appointment books that fall outside the scope of the Secretary of Commerce period. The second largest series in the collection, the Speeches Series contain drafts, frequently annotated and accompanied by other material, of Kreps's lectures, speeches, and remarks on occasions such as academic conferences, university commencements, various other university events, and corporate executive board meetings. The subjects are broadly based and reflect her interests in economics, especially in aging and older workers, women's social conditions and education, the value of women's labor, women in the corporate world, and work and leisure issues. Speeches given after her tenure as Secretary of Commerce also cover broader issues about globalization and domestic and international economic policy.
Albeit small, the Correspondence Series spans several decades and documents Kreps's exchanges with academics and scholars, the local and federal governments, and lobbyist groups. Other correspondence documents Kreps's career positions, some more fully than others, including Secretary of Commerce; Duke University Dean of the Woman's College, especially relating to the merger of the Woman's College and Trinity College; Public Director of the New York Stock Exchange Board; Women's Research and Education Institute Board of Directors; and Carter Presidential Center fundraiser. The Appointment Books and Calendars Series records Kreps's busy schedule of events and engagements, and the Publications Series holds her contributions to academic journals, government publications, and books. The Visual Material Series houses images that date from her childhood through her long career; photos taken during her cabinet position are found in the Secretary of Commerce series. Other Files Series contains materials that fall out of the above series, such as teaching materials and publicity clippings.
Collection Arrangement
Organized into the following series: Appointment Books and Calendars, Correspondence, Secretary of Commerce, Publications, Speeches, Visual Material, and Other Files. In addition to the appointment books, correspondences, and speeches in the general files, there are also similar formats embedded in the Secretary of Commerce Series that specifically belong to that period in Kreps's career.
Related Material
Woman's College Records, 1928-1974 (University Archives)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Speeches; Photograph albums; Scrapbooks; Black-and-white photographs; Black-and-white negatives; Color photographs; Color negatives; Women -- United States -- Economic conditions; Work; Cabinet officers -- United States; Aging; Executive departments -- United States; Economists -- United States -- History; Feminism -- United States -- History; Leisure; Older people -- Employment; Sexual division of labor; Women -- Education; Women economists -- United States -- History; Women -- Employment; Women executives -- United States; Duke University -- History -- 20th century; New York Stock Exchange -- History -- 20th century; United States. Dept. of Commerce -- Officials and employees; Kreps, Juanita Morris; Duke University. Woman's College
- Appointment Books and Calendars, 1973-1999, 2 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Appointment books and calendars, excluding those from Kreps's tenure as Secretary of Commerce, which are in the Secretary of Commerce Series. Calendars include daily schedules of meetings and appointments, as well as a record of her trips. Arranged in chronological order.
  - Appointment books, calendars, and similar items, 1973-1999 (Box 1-2)
- Correspondence Series, 1968-2001, 4 boxes
  Consists of incoming and outgoing correspondence that falls outside the scope of the Secretary of Commerce Series, which also has a subseries of correspondence. Arranged in chronological order except for the first folder containing her curriculum vitae. The folders with a date title contain various letters regarding intradepartmental announcements, invitations to meetings and dinners, recommendation letters, and the network of female academicians. The "Personal" folder holds letters from friends, offers for a post, and her curriculum vitae. Of particular interest are the documents related to the merger of Woman's College and Trinity College, which includes extensive opinions and expressions of support or disapproval from alumni and Kreps's responses as the Dean of the Woman's College at the time. Most correspondents in the "Carter Center" folders are incoming letters such as ones noting Kreps's support for President Carter's peace work and brochures about the Center. Material on the Women's Research and Education Institute contain incoming letters concerning board meetings and other business. Folder titles are original. Arranged in chronolgical order.
  - Curriculum Vitae, 1972 (Box 2)
  - 1968 Aug.-Sep. (Box 2)
  - 1968 Oct.-Dec. (Box 2)
  - 1969 Jan.-Feb. (Box 2)
  - 1969 Mar.-Apr. (Box 3)
  - Personal, 1969 Sept.-1972 Sept. (Box 3)
  - Temperance Society, 1970 June-Sept. (Box 3)
  - On the proposed merger of Woman's College and Trinity College of Duke University, 1971 Nov.-1972 Feb. (Box 3)
  - Departmental issues and recommendations, 1972 Feb.-1973 Oct. (Box 3)
  - J.C. Penney, 1972 May (Box 3)
  - Congratulations on New York Stock Exchange Board appointment, 1972 June-Nov., 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Positions and appointments declined, 1972 July-1973 Oct. (Box 3)
  - Positions and appointments accepted or pending, 1972 Aug. (Box 3)
  - 1972 Sept.-Dec. (Box 3)
  - 1973 Jan.-Mar. (Box 3)
  - 1973 Apr.-June, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - 1973 July-Sept. (Box 4)
  - Duke University Retirement Policy, 1974 Feb. (Box 4)
  - New York Stock Exchange, 1974 Mar.-1975 (Box 4)
  - Southern Economic Association, 1974 Apr.-1975 Oct. (Box 4)
  - R.J. Reynolds financial data, 1974 Sept.-1976 Jun. (Box 4)
  - American Assembly, Women and the American Economy, 1975 Feb.-1976 Aug. (Box 4)
  - University of North Carolina Campus Y, 1981 Mar. (Box 4)
  - Carter Center, 1981-2001, 1-2 of 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Carter Center, 1981-2001, 3 of 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Women's Research and Education Institute, 1981-1996, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Democratic Party Advisory Panel on Growth and Opportunity, 1982 (Box 5)
  - Democratic Caucus, 1983-1988 (Box 5)
  - Clinton/Gore, 1993-1999 (Box 5)
  - Women's Research and Education Institute Information, 1999-2001, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Women's Research and Education Institute Packet, 2001 (Box 5)
- Publications Series, 1962-1980 and undated, 1 box
  Contains Kreps's writings in the form of books, case studies, and articles published in government periodicals and academic journals. In original order as mantained by Kreps, in alphabetical order by topic.
  - Aging issues, 1962-1978 and undated, 1 of 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Aging issues, 1962-1978 and undated, 2-4 of 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Aging paper for Retirement Policy in an Aging Society, 1980 (Box 6)
  - Aging worker issues, 1964-1971 (Box 6)
  - A Case Study of Variable in Retirement Policy, 1961 (Box 6)
  - Economic Growth and Retirement Income (Blackburn and Kreps), undated (Box 6)
  - Leisure and work issues, 1966-1969 and undated, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Leisure Correlates of Economic Growth, undated (Box 6)
  - Manpower and Welfare Programs (Annual Meeting, Industrial Relations Research Association), 1963 (Box 6)
  - Sex, Age, Work (New York Times), 1976 (Box 6)
  - Stationary Population and the Elderly (NSF Papers), 1975 (Box 6)
  - Reviews of Sex in the Marketplace, 1971 (Box 6)
  - The Woman Professional in Higher Education, 1972 (Box 6)
- Secretary of Commerce Series, 1976-1980 and undated, 27 boxes
  Consists of the following subseries: Appointment Books and Calendars, Appointment and Confirmation Process, Correspondence, Notes, Subject Files, Photographs, and Scrapbooks. Materials in this series are dated from 1976-1980, the years during which Kreps served as Secretary of Commerce. The Appointment Books and Calendar Subseries and the Appointment and Confirmation Process Subseries are both arranged chronologically, while the remaining subseries are in alphabetical order. The Correspondence Subseries is dated 1976-1979 and chiefly contains correspondences with business leaders, government officials, and leaders of various organizations. [insert names of offices, people, events, etc., anything you feel should be highlighted or that succinctly describes the nature of the correspondence.] Notes of the Secretary Subseries contains cabinet meeting notes and minutes, speech notes, talking points, and various Commerce Department memoranda sent by Kreps. Subject files include notes and correspondence, arranged by the organization name or subject. Folders titled with an organization name will either contain her remarks at an event or notes for a meeting; for example, The Automobile Industry, Pulp and Paper Industry, and Machine Tool Industry have folders that include briefing books for her meetings with these groups. Folders titled with issues generally contain notes or talking points on that issue. Of significance is her work on the reorganization of the Commerce Department. The Photographs Subseries contains includes publicity photographs, photos and photo albums from trips abroad, and portraits. The folder entitled "Secretary of Commerce Publicity photos contains photographs of Kreps on Meet the Press as well as with Congressmen, cabinet members, and President Carter.
  - Appointment Books and Calendars Subseries
    - Appointment book, 1978, 1 of 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Appointment book, 1978, 2-3 of 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Appointment book, 1979 (Box 7)
    - Pocket calendars, 1976-1977 (Box 7)
    - Calendar, 1978 (Box 7)
    - Guestbook, 1977-1979 (Box 7)
    - Phone Log, 1977-1979 (Box 7)
  - Appointment and Confirmation Process Subseries
    - Biography of Juanita Kreps, 25th Secretary of Commerce, undated (Box 7)
    - Congratulatory letters with incomplete names and addresses, 1976 (Box 7)
    - Description of the Office of Secretary of Commerce (Box 7)
    - Friends' congratulatory letters, replies sent, 1976 (Box 7)
    - Hearings before Senate Committee on Commerce regarding Kreps's nomination, 1977 Jan. 10 (Box 7)
    - Information requested by Senate Committee on Commerce, 1977 Jan. (Box 7)
    - Letters recommending Kreps to Cabinet positions, 1976-1977 (Box 8)
    - Kreps's opening remarks to Senate Committee on Commerce, 1977 Jan. 10 (Box 8)
    - Questions and Answers for Senate Committee on Commerce, 1977 Jan. 10 (Box 8)
    - Kreps's response to Cabinet appointment, Plains, Georgia, 1976 (Box 8)
    - Statement by Kreps before Senate Committee on Commerce, 1977 Jan. 10 (Box 8)
    - Kreps's transition notes, 1977 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence as Secretary of Commerce Subseries
    - A correspondences, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - B correspondences, 1-5 of 6 folders (Box 8)
    - B correspondences, 6 of 6 folders (Box 9)
    - C correspondences, 5 folders (Box 9)
    - President Carter (Box 9)
    - D correspondences, 1-2 of 5 folders (Box 9)
    - D correspondences, 3-5 of 5 folders (Box 10)
    - E correspondences, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Eizenstat, Stuart E., 1977 (Box 10)
    - F correspondences, 3 folders (Box 10)
    - Forlines, John (Box 10)
    - G correspondences, 1-2 of 3 folders (Box 10)
    - G correspondence, 3 of 3 folders (Box 11)
    - H correspondence, 8 folders (Box 11)
    - Harman, Sidney, 1976-1978 (Box 11)
    - Hodges, Luther, Jr., 1977-1979 (Box 11)
    - Hunt, Governor James B., 1978-1979 (Box 11)
    - I correspondence, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - J correspondence, 4 folders (Box 12)
    - Jerry Jasinowski, 1978 and undated (Box 12)
    - K correspondence, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - L correspondence, 1 of 3 folders (Box 12)
    - L correspondence, 2-3 of 3 folders (Box 13)
    - Letters from White House, Congressmen, Governors, Senators, 3 folders (Box 13)
    - M correspondence, 1-4 of 6 folders (Box 13)
    - M correspondence, 5-6 of 6 folders (Box 14)
    - N correspondence, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - O correspondence, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - P correspondence, 3 folders (Box 14)
    - Q correspondence (Box 14)
    - R correspondence, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Roosa, Robert V., 1977 (Box 15)
    - S correspondence, 4 folders (Box 15)
    - T correspondence, 1 of 2 folders (Box 15)
    - T correspondence, 2 of 2 folders (Box 16)
    - U correspondence (Box 16)
    - V correspondence (Box 16)
    - W correspondence, 3 folders (Box 16)
    - X correspondence (Box 16)
    - Y correspondence (Box 16)
    - Z correspondence (Box 16)
  - Notes of the Secretary Subseries
    - Cabinet meetings, 1977, 1-2 of 4 folders (Box 16)
    - Cabinet meetings, 1977, 3-4 of 4 folders (Box 17)
    - Cabinet notes, 1979-1980 (Box 17)
    - Notes of the Secretary - miscellanesous, 1977-1979, 4 folders (Box 17)
  - Subject Files Subseries
    - Affidavits, 1978 Mar. (Box 17)
    - Aging, 1978 Jul. (Box 17)
    - American Retail Federation briefing book, 1979 Feb. 15 (Box 17)
    - Anti-inflation, 1978 (Box 18)
    - Autograph requests sent, 1979 (Box 18)
    - Automobile industry meeting, 1979 Mar. 14 (Box 18)
    - Budget, Department of Commerce, 1978 (Box 18)
    - Business Council and Business Leaders (Box 18)
    - Business Council/Business Roundtable notes, 1977-1978 (Box 18)
    - Calls to key members of Senate Committee on Commerce, 1977 (Box 18)
    - Candidates for Commerce positions, 1977 (Box 18)
    - Candidates for Under Secretary, 1977-1978 (Box 18)
    - Carter Economic recovery package (Box 18)
    - China, 1979 Jun. (Box 18)
    - Commerce Council, 1977-1978 (Box 18)
    - Commerce Department Employees Annual Honor Awards Ceremoney, remarks by Kreps, 1979 Oct. 30 (Box 18)
    - Kreps's Commerce Employment, 1977 (Box 18)
    - Congressional Record, 1977 Feb. 1 (Box 18)
    - Corporate Social Performance, 1979 (Box 18)
    - Council on Foreign Relations, 1979 Nov. 1 (Box 18)
    - Democratic Mid-term Convention, 1978 Dec. 8-10 (Box 18)
    - Equipment exports of Soviet Union (Box 18)
    - JMK's recommendation of Sidney Harman to Carter, 1979 (Box 19)
    - Dr. Sidney Harman's nomination, 1977 Jan. (Box 19)
    - Hospital Cost Containment, 1977-1978 (Box 19)
    - Information for speeches (Box 19)
    - Japan, 1978 Oct. (Box 19)
    - Joint Economic Committee, 1979 (Box 19)
    - Machine Tool Industry meeting briefing books, 1979 Mar. 7 (Box 19)
    - Maritime, 1977 (Box 19)
    - Kreps's memberships, 1977-1979 (Box 19)
    - Minorities, 1977-1978 (Box 19)
    - North Carolina - tobacco issue, 1978 (Box 19)
    - Pulp and Paper Industry meeting, 1978 Oct. 24 (Box 19)
    - Regulatory reform, 1978 (Box 19)
    - Reorganization (of Commerce Department), 1978-1979 (Box 19)
    - Requests for information, 1977-1978 (Box 19)
    - Saturday Review article on Chrysler, 1979 Nov. 21 (Box 19)
    - Statements before House and Senate Committees, 1979 Oct. 31-Nov. 1 (Box 19)
    - Staff evaluations, 1979 (Box 19)
    - Notes on stimulus package, Plains, Georgia, undated (Box 19)
    - JMK talking points with Secretary Richardson, 1977 Jan. 5 (Box 19)
    - Tax reform, 1978 (Box 19)
    - Textiles, 1978-1979 (Box 20)
    - UNC (University of North Carolina)- H.E.W. (Department of Health, Education, and Welfare) issues, 1978-1979 (Box 20)
    - United States Department of Commerce News, 1977-1979 (Box 20)
    - U.S.S.R. trip notes, 1978 Dec. (Box 20)
    - White House conference on balanced national growth, 1978 June (Box 20)
    - Wolf Trap fundraiser for businessmen hosted by Juanita M. Kreps, 1978 July 27 (Box 20)
    - Women's issues, 1977 (Box 20)
  - Photographs Subseries
    - Secretary of Commerce publicity, 8 folders (Box 51)
    - China, undated (Box 52)
    - The European Commission, Brussels, Belgium, 1979 Sep. 24 (Box 52)
    - President Carter bill signing, undated (Box 52)
    - Third Tunisian-American Joint Commission, Tunis, 1979 Mar. 30-31 (Box 52)
    - Beijing, China, undated (Box 52)
    - Japan visit, undated (Box 52)
    - "Group 13" (Box 52)
    - "Group 14" (Box 52)
    - "Group 15" (Box 52)
    - "Group 16" (Box 52)
    - Secretary of Commerce 1978 Dec. - 1979 Feb., 2 folders (Box 52)
    - Photos from Walter Mondale (Box 52)
    - Warsaw, Poland, 1977 Nov. 28-Dec. 2 (Box 52)
    - "Group 22" (Box 52)
    - Berlin, undated (Box 52)
    - Geneva, undated (Box 52)
    - Japan, undated (Box 53)
    - Greetings, 1979 and undated (Box 53)
    - Visits to Foreign Countries, undated (Box 53)
    - "Group 31", 3 folders (Box 53)
    - India, 1978 (Box 54)
    - Poland, undated, 2 albums (Box 54)
    - Union Gas Plant Dedication album, Korea, 1977 Sep. 29 (Box 54)
    - U.S. Merchant Marine Academy graduation album, 1978 Aug. 23 (Box 55)
    - Saudi Arabia, 1979 (Box 55)
    - China, May 1979, 2 albums (Box 56)
    - Secretary of Commerce photos, 1977 Jan. (Box 56)
    - American-Romanian Economic Commission meeting, Washington, D.C., 1977 Nov. (Box 56)
    - Kreps's visit to China, May 1979 (Box 57)
    - China, undated (1976?) (Box 57)
    - Japan, 1978 Oct., 2 folders (Box 57)
    - Scrapbooks Subseries, 12 volumes (Oversize-box 21-32)
    - Clippings, 1976 Dec.-1977 Feb. (Box 21)
    - Photos, 1977 Jan.-1977 Aug. (Box 22)
    - Clippings, 1977 Feb.-1977 May (Box 23)
    - Clippings, 1977 June-1977 Aug. (Box 24)
    - Photos, 1977 Sept.-1978 Jan. (Box 25)
    - Clippings, 1977 Sept.-1977 Dec. (Box 26)
    - Photos in the Warsaw visit, 1977 Nov.-1977 Dec. (Box 27)
    - Clippings, 1978 Jan.-1978 Mar. (Box 28)
    - Clippings, 1978 Apr.-1978 June (Box 29)
    - Clippings, 1978 June-1978 Oct. (Box 30)
    - Clippings, 1978 Nov.-1979 Jan. (Box 31)
    - Clippings and miscellaneous oversize materials, 1979 Feb.-1979 Aug. and undated (Box 32)
- Speeches Series, 1962-1999 and undated, 18 boxes
  Contains many folders of speeches to students and parents as dean of the Woman's College at Duke University, commencement addresses, invited lectures, paper presentations at conferences, addresses to various organizations and business groups, keynote addresses at symposiums, and two television interviews (1992). Topics often concern women in the workforce and aging issues. itles of speeches in Miscellaneous speech folder include:
  - Consumer Behavior in the 1960s, 1962 (Box 33)
  - Economic Change and the Status of Women, N.C. Council of Women's Organizations address, 1962 Jul. 19 (Box 33)
  - The Allocation of Intellect, Wake County Assoc. of Phi Beta Kappa, 1962 Oct. 22 (Box 33)
  - Wednesday Literary Club, Greensboro, 1963 May 1 (Box 33)
  - Scholarship in the Soaring Sixties, Berea College, 1963 May (Box 33)
  - Economic Implications of Shortened Work Life, 6th International Congress of Gerontology - Copenhagen, 1963 Aug. (Box 33)
  - The Mass Market and Individual Choices; or, The Case of the Homogenized Consumer, American Association of University Women (AAUW), 1964 May (Box 33)
  - Benefit-Cost Analysis: A Comment, Manpower and Welfare Programs: Benefit-Cost Analysis, Chicago, 1964 Dec. (Box 33)
  - Adjustment of the Aged to a Changing Economic Environment, American Orthopsychiatric Assoc., 1965 Mar. (Box 33)
  - What's Wrong with Men? Kiwanis Club, 1966 Feb. 14 (Box 33)
  - Women, Wise and Otherwise, Western Reserve University, 1966 Oct. 20 (Box 33)
  - Southern Women, Conference on the Changing South, 1967 Jan. (Box 33)
  - The Changing Concept of Work, Cornell College, 1967 Nov. (Box 33)
  - Higher Incomes for Older Americans, NCOA address, 1968 Mar. 5 (Box 33)